Guide to the William Francis Dunne Papers TAM.145
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
William Francis Dunne Papers
1914-1951
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Dunne, William Francis, 1887-1953
Gerson, Simon W.
Gerson, Deborah
TAM.145
2.25 Linear Feet in four manuscript boxes and 3 folders.
William F. Dunne was a Marist-Leninist labor organizer and politician. The collection consists mainly of manuscripts, correspondence, newspaper clippings, speeches, photographs, and reports. Series I features a scrapbook which documents Dunne's life and activities in Butte. Most of the correspondence in series II is with his wife Marguerite, and dates from his Navy service in the Aleutian Islands, 1944-45. Prominent Communist correspondents include William Z. Foster, Mike Gold and Sam Darcy. Series III contains speeches, clippings, reports and other materials documenting Dunne's activities in Butte, and his expulsion from the Communist Party. Series IV contains brief statements of Dunne's views on current events, the labor movement, criticism of the Communist Party and open letters to individuals and publications. Series V, Manuscripts, comprises half the collection. These often undated pieces were written from the mid-1930's onward, after Dunne's role in the CPUSA was diminished.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Simon Gerson in 1991 and 1992; additional photographs were donated by Gerson's daughter, Deborah Gerson, in 2008. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1950.250, 1992.001, NPA.2002.027, and NPA.2008.018.
Arrangement
Organized into six series:
Series I: Biography and Autobiographies
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Activities
Series IV: Proposals, Statements, Articles and Notes
Series V: Manuscripts
Series VI: Portraits and Photographs
Folders are arranged chronologically within series.
Historical/Biographical Note
William Francis Dunne (1887-1953) was a labor organizer, politician, editor, and Communist Party activist for most of his life. Born in 1887 in Kansas City, Missouri, Dunne was a football player at the University of Minnesota. As a result of the Panic of 1907, Dunne dropped out of college to become an electrician. He worked for the Northern Pacific Railway until 1910, when he joined the Socialist Party. Dunne was a middleweight boxer of some local note in 1914. In this period he was elected Business Agent of the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers in Vancouver and eventually vice-president of the Pacific District Council of the IBEW. He resigned after several years and in 1916, moved to Butte, Montana. There he married Marguerite Walsh, circa 1918. William and Marguerite Dunne had one son, William Jr., who was killed in 1925 at the age of seven by a speeding car.
In Butte, Dunne worked for several copper mining companies. He worked for the Anaconda Copper Mining Company in 1917 when 164 men were smothered to death. As a Joint Chairman of the Miners and Metal Trades Mechanics Strike Committee, Dunne participated in leading a strike of 28,000 men against the mining company. In 1918, Dunne became vice-president of the Montana Federation of Labor and was elected to the Montana State legislature as a Democrat on a radical platform. He introduced the first resolution in any United States legislative body calling for the withdrawal of American troops from Siberia and for recognition of the Soviet Union. That same year, Dunne became editor of the newly-founded Butte Daily Bulletin, the official organ of the Butte Central Labor Council. He remained editor until 1922. It was also during this period that Dunne, along with Louis Lochner of the Milwaukee Leader, Leland Olds, and Carl Haessler, founded the Federated Press, a labor news service.
During the 1920's Dunne was an organizer for several unions, among them the Steel and Metal Workers Union, out of which developed the United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers Union. He took part in the organizing work of the International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers, and organized the defense of the Gastonia textile union organizers in 1929-1930. Also in this period, Dunne was a national organizer for William Foster's Trade Union Unity League and the national hunger marches of the unemployed councils. Elected in 1924 as an alternate member of the Executive Committee of the Communist International, Dunne was the representative of the Workers (Communist) Party of America to the Comintern in 1925. He returned to the Soviet Union in 1928 to participate in Congresses of the Profintern and the Comintern, and in 1928-1929 served as a Comintern delegate in Outer Mongolia, allegedly collecting data on Japanese intrigue in the region.
Dunne was added to the Politburo in 1929, but with Earl Browder's rise to Party leadership in the early 1930's, Dunne's party influence weakened. In 1934, Dunne returned to Butte, after he was dismissed from his national leadership position. For the next six years, he had a somewhat insignificant party role. He did occasional reporting for the Daily Worker and N ew Masses, and did organizational and publicity work for the Party throughout the Pacific Northwest region. Beginning in this period, Dunne focused much of his activity on writing. Many of his writings remained unpublished though he completed several political pamphlets and a major study of the African-American press for a film company. Since Browder's rise to leadership, and especially with the onset of the Popular Front in 1935, Dunne was extremely dissatisfied with the direction of the Party, maintaining that its' positions were too moderate and revisionist. Dunne often had many complaints about the course of the American Party, asserting that it had abdicated it's role as a vanguard party. However, he frequently affirmed the positions of the Soviet Union and the Comintern, for example, his hearty endorsement of the 1939 Nazi-Soviet Pact. By the late 1930's, Dunne's alcoholism became out of control; in the late 1930's he caused much internal Party strife when he told comrades that Browder was planning to liquidate the Party.
With the outbreak of World War II, Dunne worked in war related industries and shipyards. From 1944 until the beginning of 1946, he found work as a navy cook in the Aleutian Islands. Upon Dunne's return to the United States, the Communist Party expelled him for "ultra-leftism" and alcoholism. Dunne, along with other expelled communists Max Bedacht, Vern Smith, and Samuel Darcy, unsuccessfully appealed this decision to the Cominform. Dunne maintained contact with other expelled communist leaders and attempted to form another independent communist party in the late 1940's. In 1951, Dunne helped found the James Connolly Association, an Irish Republican organization. William Dunne died in 1953.
Related Materials
The Jefferson School of Social Science (New York, N.Y.) Records and Indexes (TAM 005)
Sam Adams Darcy Papers (TAM 124)
A portion of the photographs were deaccessioned and given to the Elmer E. Rasmuson Library, University of Alaska Fairbanks. The collection is called: USUAFV6-339. Dunne, William F. Photograph Collection.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Dunne span the years 1914-1951, with the bulk of the material from 1918-1946. The collection consists mainly of unpublished manuscripts, statements, and short articles intended for publication. Also included in the collection are correspondence, newspaper clippings, speeches, photographs, and reports. Most of the material was written by Dunne, but segments of manuscripts and reports were written by other individuals such as Alphaeus Hunton and Samuel Darcy. The collection provides a good cross-section of material from Dunne's activities and writings, documenting Dunne's shifting political and ideological positions as well as the changes he experienced within the communist movement. The collection provides little information about Dunne's activities abroad, his travel through Europe, several trips to the Soviet Union, and time spent in Outer Mongolia. The collection provides some documentation about Dunne's activities serving in various Soviet committees such as the Profintern and the Politburo.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Researchers must use microfilm copy only (R-7121), with the exception of materials in Series VI and materials in box 4, which were not microfilmed.
Separated Material
27 photographic images were removed and donated to the University of Alaska (Fairbanks). A comic book-style pamphlet titled "Heroes in Dungarees" published by the National Maritime Union was separated to the library collection (PAM 5909).
Labor unions and communism -- United States.; Political crimes and offenses |z United States.; Working class -- Northwest, Pacific; Butte (Mont.); Scrapbooks.; Photographic prints.; Manuscripts for publication.; Labor movement -- United States.; Communist Party of the United States of America; Communist Party of the United States of America -- History; Darcy, Samuel, 1905-; Dunne, William Francis, 1887-1953; Gold, Michael, 1893-1967; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961; Keeney, Philip O. (Philip Olin), 1891-1962; Gerson, Simon W.; Gerson, Deborah
- Series I: Biography and Autobiographies, 1914-1936
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Biography and Autobiographies (1914-1936) contains several newspaper clippings about Dunne's personal life. There is a five page autobiography which Dunne sent to prospective publishers. The bulk of this series consists of Dunne's scrapbook which contained mainly newspaper clippings as well as speeches and some memorabilia from Dunne's activities in Butte, Montana and as the editor of the Butte Daily Bulletin.
  - Scrapbook: Montana Labor Activity, 1917-1925 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dunne: Biographical and Autobiographical Material, 1914-1936 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1923-1951
  Series II: Correspondence (1923-1951) contains political and personal correspondence. Most of this series is made up of letters written by Dunne to his wife from the Aleutian Islands, where he served as a navy cook from 1944 through 1945. There are also letters from Dunne's Party comrades William Foster, Mike Gold, and Sam Darcy. Also in this series is a threat from Montana vigilantes and Ku Klux Klan members addressed to Dunne.
  - Ku Klux Klan, Butte Montana, 1923 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
  - William Z. Foster, 1936 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Walter Sands, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1)
  - Arvo Fredrickson, 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1)
  - Bruce Bliven, 1938 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rejection Letters From Publishers, 1938-1948 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Michael Gold, 1939 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 9)
  - To Marguerite Dunne, 1944-1945 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 10)
  - To Marguerite Dunne, 1945 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 10.1)
  - To Marguerite Dunne, 1946-1951 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 10.2)
  - Marguerite Dunne to William Francis Dunne, 1948-1949 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Darcy Expulsion, Letter to William Foster, 1945 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sam Darcy, 1948 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Unnamed, 1948-1950 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series III: Activities, 1917-1951
  Series III: Activities (1917-1951) contains limited information about Dunne's numerous political projects. This material is in various forms, including speeches, newspaper clippings, reports, and some letters. Most of this material refers to Dunne's activities in Butte, as well as his expulsion from the Communist Party in 1946.
  - Butte Daily Bulletin, 1917-1923 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Testimony at hearings held at the State Capitol, Helena, Montana, May 31, June 1, June 2, 1918, by the Montana Council of Defense, in connection with the arrest of Von Waldru, alias Charles Stone, by federal authorities, and also in connection with an investigation of charges against Oscar Rohn, May-Jun 1918 (Box 4)
  - Investigative Report: Centralia, WA Murder, 1920 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Michigan "Red" Raid Cases, 1923 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Expulsion Speech, AFL Convention, Portland, 1923 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Conviction Report, New York City, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 19, Reel 1)
  - Wagner Bill, NRA, Speeches, Letters, 1933-1935 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Testimony for US Senate Hearing: 30 Hour Work Week; National Labor Board, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 20.1, Reel 1)
  - Butte Activity, 1934-1954 (Box 1, Folder 21, Reel 2)
  - Philip O. Keeney: Dismissed From University of Montana, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 22, Reel 2)
  - Appeal of Expulsion From CPUSA to Cominform, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 23, Reel 2)
  - Expulsion from Communist Party: Clippings from Daily Worker, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 24, Reel 2)
  - National Maritime Union Campaign, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 25, Reel 2)
  - Connelly Association, 1951 (Reel 2, Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Poetry by Dunne, undated (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series IV: Proposals, Statements, Articles, Notes, 1919-1949
  Series IV: Proposals, Statements, Articles, and Notes (1919-1949) contains short statements of Dunne's political positions, commentary about current events, usually in the labor movement, criticism of Communist Party activities and positions, and open letters to individuals and publications. This series documents Dunne's political perspective on a variety of topics, such as the Seattle General Strike of 1919, the Nazi-Soviet Pact, Communist Party policies, and Henry Wallace's 1948 presidential campaign.
  - Labor in Pacific Northwest, Seattle General Strike: Article, 1919 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Article for New Masses: "The Red Tide in the Homeland of Genghis Khan", 1928-1929 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 3)
  - RILU Trade Union Report, Critique of Executive Council Resolution, 1930 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Discussion of AFL Convention, 1930 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 5)
  - United Mine Workers of America: Mining Industry Reports, Statements, 1933 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 6)
  - AFL Convention: Report to Daily Worker, 1935 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Articles for New Masses, 1935 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Nazi-Soviet Pact: Endorsement to Daily Worker, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 9, Reel 2)
  - Memorium, Obituaries (written for others), 1940 (Box 2, Folder 10, Reel 2)
  - Lewis-Quill Dispute in Transit Workers Union: Articles, Notes, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 11, Reel 2)
  - Draft: Expulsions of Dunne, Darcy, 1945-1949 (Box 2, Folder 12, Reel 2)
  - San Francisco Memorandum, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 13, Reel 2)
  - San Francisco Expulsions: Report from Vern Smith, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 14, Reel 2)
  - Bedacht Expulsion: Statements, Correspondence, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2)
  - Wallace Campaign: Statement of Endorsement to Progressive Citizens of America, 1948 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 16)
  - National Maritime Union: Resolutions, Draft Reports, Statements, 1949-1950 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 17)
  - AFL Convention: Proposed Resolutions, undated (Reel 3, Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Comments on Dennis Report, undated (Reel 3, Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "Detroit Racketeers in the Soviet Union" Article, undated (Reel 3, Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Open Letter to William Randolph Hearst, undated (Reel 3, Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Statement of International Longshoremen's Association Policy in Regard to Formation of Federation of Waterfront Unions, undated (Reel 3, Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "The New Opportunism" Open Letter to the Communist Party, undated (Reel 3, Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Proposals for Peoples' Government and a New Party, undated (Box 2, Folder 24, Reel 3)
  - Women and the Labor Movement, undated (Box 2, Folder 25, Reel 3)
  - Steel and Metal Workers Statement and Program, undated (Box 2, Folder 26, Reel 3)
  - Taft-Hartley Discussions, undated (Box 2, Folder 27, Reel 3)
  - Memo for Draft: AFL, undated (Box 2, Folder 28, Reel 3)
- Series V: Manuscripts, 1936-1948
  Series V: Manuscripts (1936-1948) is the largest series in the collection. Many of the manuscripts in this series are undated, however, Dunne did not begin writing manuscripts until approximately the mid-1930's. For several of the manuscripts, there are multiple drafts. Few were ever published, although Dunne made an extensive effort to publish his History of the Communist Party and Trade Unions in the United States. Dunne's Survey of the Negro Press was presumably bought by a major film company. Some of the manuscripts in this series are Catholic Doctrine and Anti-Semitism, The CPUSA and Revisionism, Hard Times Coming, and World Imperialist War.
  - Catholic Doctrine and Anti-Semitism, 15 pages, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 29, Reel 3)
  - The Supreme Court and Organized Labor, 22 pages, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 30, Reel 3)
  - Survey of Negro Press, Sections I and II, 97 pages, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 31, Reel 3)
  - Survey of Negro Press, Sections III (with Section by Alphaeus Hunton), 58 pages, 1944 (Reel 3, Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Philadelphia Transit Strike, Union Race Relations, 21 pages, 1944 (Reel 3, Box 2, Folder 33)
  - The National Committee (CPUSA) and Revisionism, 43 pages, 1946 (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Material for Dunne Booklet Facts of His Expulsion (Introduction by Sam Darcy), 24 pages, 1946 (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Revisionism of the National Committee, 78 pages, 1946 (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 3)
  - History of the Communist Party (Handwritten), 24 pages, 1948 (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Capitalist Rationalization and Unemployment, 37 pages, undated (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Catholic Church and Fascism, 39 pages, undated (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Communist Party and the AFL, 18 pages, undated (Box 3, Folder 7, Reel 4)
  - "Hard Times Coming" Draft Outline, 6 pages, undated (Box 3, Folder 8, Reel 4)
  - History of the Communist Movement in the United States, Draft 1, 35 pages, undated (Box 3, Folder 9, Reel 4)
  - History of the Communist Movement, Draft 2, 52 pages, undated (Box 3, Folder 10, Reel 4)
  - History of the Communist Movement, Draft 3, 75 pages, undated (Box 3, Folder 11, Reel 4)
  - History of the Communist Movement, Draft 4, 84 pages, undated (Box 3, Folder 12, Reel 4)
  - History of the Communist Movement, additional sections, notes, 27 pages, undated (Box 3, Folder 13, Reel 4)
  - "If This Be Treason," Draft, 23 pages, undated (Reel 4, Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "The Long War," Draft, 26 pages, undated (Reel 4, Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Monopoly Capitalism and Economic Crisis, 41 pages, undated (Reel 4, Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Too Many Lies," Draft, 69 pages, undated (Reel 4, Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Trade Unions in the United States," Outline, notes for Book, 36 pages, undated (Reel 4, Box 3, Folder 18)
  - World Imperialist War, 17 pages, undated (Reel 4, Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "War Song of Yankee Metal Workers," Introductory Note, 1 page, undated (Reel 4, Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Segments of Manuscripts, 14 pages, undated (Reel 4, Box 3, Folder 21)
- Series VI: Portraits and Photographs, undated
  Series VI: Portraits and Photographs (undated) contains three pencil portraits of Dunne by an unknown artist. The photographs consist of photographs of Dunne, his wife Marguerite, and friends. It also contains images from Butte, Montana union activities in which he was involved. Unions documented include the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, and the Metal Mine Workers Union. It also includes one print of a drawing by Art Young, of a satirical wanted poster for Jesus Christ. There are also some photographs from his trip to Mongolia in 1928.
  - Photographs, 1913-1934 (Box Shared Tamiment A004)
  - Photographs (2008 Accession), 1928-1948 (Box Shared Tamiment A004)
  - Drawing of William Dunne, Full Face, undated (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS003, Folder 1)
  - Drawing of William Dunne, Left Profile, undated (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS003, Folder 1)
  - Drawing of William Dunne, Right Profile, undated (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS003, Folder 1)